Guide to the Gustavus Vasa Fox Collection 1823-1919 (bulk 1860-1889) MS 439.17
New-York Historical Society
Gustavus Vasa Fox Collection
1823-1919 (bulk 1860-1889)
New-York Historical Society
MS 439.17
10 Linear feet (21 boxes, 15 volumes)
The collection includes correspondence, personal papers and documents, financial records, speeches and writings, memorabilia and souvenirs, printed materials, and clippings of Gustavus Vasa Fox during his tenure as Assistant Secretary of the Navy and afterwards; correspondence of his wife Virginia Woodbury Fox; and correspondence and personal papers pertaining to other Woodbury and Fox family members. The materials in this collection have been digitized and are available online to on-site researchers and to users affiliated with subscribing institutions via EBSCOhost.
Provenance
Donated to the New-York Historical Society by the Naval History Society in 1925.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.)
Biographical Note
Gustavus Vasa Fox (1821-1883) read law with his future wife's uncle, Isaac O. Barnes, in 1837 and began his maritime career as a midshipman in 1838. He served in various naval and mercantile vessels before retiring in 1856 to manage the Bay State Woolen Mills in Lawrence, Massachusetts. His suggestions for the relief of Fort Sumter were not followed, but through connections to Abraham Lincoln via Postmaster Montgomery Blair (his wife's brother-in-law) he was appointed Assistant Secretary of the Navy under Gideon Welles in 1861. He served in that position through the Civil War, functioning as de facto chief of naval operations. He championed the cause of ironclad fighting ships, supporting John Ericsson (see Series 16) in his bid to build Monitor. Fox is credited with improving the management of the Navy that made possible its wartime victories.
In 1866 he made the first transatlantic voyage in an ironclad (Miantonomoh) to deliver a congressional resolution to Tsar Alexander II, congratulating him on his escape from an assassination attempt. The ship made extensive stops in European ports en route. In 1867 he made an unsuccessful attempt to take over the Southwest Pacific railroad, the forerunner of the St. Louis-San Francisco railroad. In 1869 he began management of Middlesex Mills in Lowell, Massachusetts, moving to Boston in 1874 from where he commuted to Lawrence to manage Washington Mills for the commission house of Mudge, Sawyer, and Co. He retired in 1878 and pursued interests that included documenting Columbus's first landfall in the new world, and the local history and topography of New Hampshire.
Scope and Content Note
The collection includes correspondence, personal papers and documents, financial records, speeches and writings, memorabilia and souvenirs, printed materials, and clippings of Gustavus Vasa Fox; correspondence of his wife Virginia Woodbury Fox; and correspondence and personal papers pertaining to other Woodbury and Fox family members. The materials in this collection have been digitized and are available online to on-site researchers and to users affiliated with subscribing institutions via EBSCOhost.
The Gustavus Vasa Fox Collection forms Series 17 of the Naval History Society Collection, comprising 53 individual collections named for famous naval figures and ships, as well as the records of the Naval History Society itself, and donated to the New-York Historical Society by the Naval History Society in 1925.
Arrangement
The materials are arranged in 10 series, each of which is arranged chronologically unless otherwise described in its Scope and Content note. Many of the series were previously edited and arranged by Virginia Woodbury Fox and/or Colonel Robert Thompson in preparation for the latter's editing and publication of Fox's letters ("The Fox Papers, being the confidential correspondence of Gustavus V. Fox, Assistant Secretary of the Navy during the Civil War," Vols. I and II, edited by Colonel Robert M. Thompson and Rear Admiral Richard Wainwright and printed by DeVinne Press, New York, as the ninth and tenth volumes of the Society's publications) in 1918 and 1919. In some series, pages were numbered in order in pencil; in others Mrs. Fox has included notes about materials that she destroyed, erased, or otherwise redacted.
The series are:
Missing Title
Series I. Correspondence
Series II. Personal papers and documents
Series III. Speeches and writings
Series IV. Financial records
Series V. Memorabilia, souvenirs, and visual materials
Series VI. Printed materials and clippings
Series VII. Virginia L. Woodbury Fox papers
Series VIII. Woodbury and Fox family papers
Series IX. Archival and filing records
Series X. Bound volumes
Lowell (Mass.) -- Industries.; Correspondence.; Photographic prints.; Lawrence (Mass.) -- History.; Kearsage (Mount, Merrimack County, N.H.); Books; Calling cards; Scrapbooks.; Commissions (orders for works).; Coupons; Currency; Drawings (visual works); Diorama maps; Engraving plates; Ephemera.; Clippings (information artifacts); Tickets.; Pennants; Maps.; Letters (correspondence); Invitations.; Financial records.; Building plans.; Account books.; Diaries.; United States -- Foreign relations -- Russia.; Russia -- Foreign relations -- United States.; Russia -- Description and travel.; New Hampshire -- History, Local.; Blair, Montgomery, 1813-1883; Columbus, Christopher -- Landfall; Ericsson, John, 1803-1889; Farragut, David Glasgow, 1801-1870; Fox, Gustavus Vasa, 1821-1883; Meigs, Montgomery C. (Montgomery Cunningham), 1816-1892; Monitor (Ironclad); Paulding, James K. (James Kirke), 1778-1860; Stimers, Alban C., 1827-1876; St. John's Church (Portsmouth, N.H.); United States. Navy -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Woodbury, Levi, 1789-1851
- Series I. Correspondence (1838-1883)
  Scope and Contents note
  The correspondence includes incoming and outgoing letters, a small amount of which is personal and the bulk from Fox's tenure as Assistant Secretary of the Navy. Some of the originals were rearranged and annotated by Virginia Woodbury Fox. Her notes indicate that she destroyed those she believed to be too personal. Marie Bayless, librarian of the Naval History Society, may have typed the transcripts as part of the letters' editing by Col. Thompson. Also included are letters received by James Paulding, Assistant Secretary of the Navy before Fox. No explanation is given for their presence in the collection.
  The early letters received (1838-1860) are mostly orders to report to ships for duty, and include Fox's recommendation as a midshipman, signed by John Quincy Adams when he served as a representative from Massachusetts after his presidency. Among those in 1861 is one from Abraham Lincoln. Fox's other correspondents include John Ericsson (see Series 16) and General Ulysses S. Grant. The Civil War-era letters document routine activities of the Navy: orders, reports of activities, discussion of policy, personnel, and maneuvers. The later letters include correspondence regarding Fox's donation to St. John's Episcopal Church, Portsmouth, New Hampshire, of a credence table (to hold items required to celebrate Communion) made from the oak timbers of Admiral David Farragut's flagship Hartford.
  Arrangement
  Some of the correspondence was arranged by month within a year and some by last name of recipient within a year. The original order has been retained.
  - Letters sent: Virginia Woodbury Fox, 1860 June 21 - 1861 October 16 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letters sent: Virginia Woodbury Fox, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters sent: Virginia Woodbury Fox, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters sent: Virginia Woodbury Fox, 1864-1865 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters sent: Virginia Woodbury Fox, 1867-1873 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letters sent, 1861 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Letters sent: A,B, 1862 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Letters sent: C, 1862 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Letters sent: D, 1862 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Letters sent: E, 1862 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Letters sent: F, 1862 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Letters sent: G, 1862 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Letters sent: H-K, 1862 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Letters sent: L, 1862 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Letters sent: M,O, 1862 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Letters sent: P,R, 1862 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Letters sent: S, 1862 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Letters sent: T,U,W, 1862 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Letters sent: typescripts, 1862 September - December (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Letters sent, 1863 January (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Letters sent, 1863 February (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Letters sent, 1863 March (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Letters sent, 1863 April (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Letters sent, 1863 May (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Letters sent, 1863 June (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Letters sent, 1863 July (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Letters sent, 1863 August (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Letters sent, 1863 September (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Letters sent, 1863 October (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Letters sent, 1863 November - December (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Letters sent: B, 1864 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Letters sent: C-E, 1864 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Letters sent: F-H, 1864 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Letters sent: General Grant, 1864 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Letters sent: J-M, 1864 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Letters sent: O,P,R,S, 1864 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Letters sent: W, 1864 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Letters sent: A-C, 1865 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Letters sent: E-G, 1865 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Letters sent: H, J-M, 1865 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Letters sent: P,R-T,V, 1865 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Letters sent: W, 1865 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Letters sent, 1866-1867 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Letters sent, 1868 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Letters received, 1838-1849 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Letters received by James Kirk Paulding, Secretary of the Navy, 1840 - 1841 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Letters received, 1850 - 1860 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Letters received, 1861 January - April (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Letters received, 1861 May - July (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Letters received, 1861 August - October (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Letters received, 1861 November (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Letters received, 1861 December (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Letters received: A,B, 1862 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Letters received: C, 1862 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Letters received: D,E, 1862 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Letters received: Samuel Dupont, 1862 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Letters received: John Ericsson, 1862 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Letters received: John Ericsson, typescripts, 1862 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Letters received: F, 1862 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Letters received: G, 1862 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Letters received: H-K, 1862 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Letters received: L, 1862 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Letters received: M, 1862 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Letters received: N-P, 1862 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Letters received: Porter, 1862 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Letters received: R, 1862 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Letters received: S, 1862 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Letters received: Alban Stimers, 1862 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Letters received: Alban Stimers, typescript, 1862 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Letters received: T,U, 1862 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Letters received: W, 1862 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Letters received: B-H, typescript, 1862 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Letters received: M-W, typescript, 1862 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Letters received: A,B, 1863 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Letters received: C, 1863 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Letters received: D, 1863 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Letters received: E, 1863 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Letters received: FA - J.M. Forbes, 1863 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Letters received: P. Forbes - Fulton, 1863 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Letters received: Gi - Gr, 1863 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Letters received: Gu, 1863 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Letters received: H, 1863 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Letters received: J-L, 1863 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Letters received: M-O, 1863 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Letters received: P, 1863 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Letters received: R, 1863 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Letters received: S, 1863 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Letters received: T,U, 1863 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Letters received: W, 1863 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Letters received: A, 1864 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Letters received: B, 1864 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Letters received: C, 1864 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Letters received: C.W. Copeland, 1864 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Letters received: D, 1864 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Letters received: E, 1864 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Letters received: J.B. Eads, 1864 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Letters received: John Ericsson, 1864 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Letters received: F, 1864 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Letters received: D.G. Farragut, 1864 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Letters received: J.S. Fay, 1864 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Letters received: J.M. Forbes, 1864 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Letters received: R.B. Forbes, 1864 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Letters received: G, 1864 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Letters received: F.H Gregory, 1864 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Letters received: J.W Grimes, 1864 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Letters received: H-K, 1864 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Letters received: T.A. Jenkins, 1864 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Letters received: J.W. King, 1864 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Letters received: L, 1864 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Letters received: W.K. Latimer, 1864 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Letters received: R.B. Loury, 1864 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Letters received: M, 1864 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Letters received: N,O, 1864 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Letters received: P, 1864 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Letters received: D.D. Porter, 1864 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Letters received: Q,R, 1864 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Letters received: S, 1864 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Letters received: Alban Stimers, 1864 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Letters received: C.K. Stribling, 1864 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Letters received: T, 1864 (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Letters received: U,V, 1864 (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Letters received: W, 1864 (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Letters received: A. Wise, 1864 (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Letters received: A,B, 1865 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Letters received: C, 1865 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Letters received: D, 1865 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Letters received: E, 1865 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Letters received: F, 1865 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Letters received: G, 1865 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Letters received: H-K, 1865 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Letters received: L, 1865 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Letters received: M,N, 1865 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Letters received: O, 1865 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Letters received: P, 1865 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Letters received: R, 1865 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Letters received: S, 1865 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Letters received: T, 1865 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Letters received: U-Y, 1865 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Letters received: A, 1866 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Letters received: B, 1866 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Letters received: C-F, 1866 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Letters received: G-K, 1866 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Letters received: L-R, 1866 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Letters received: D.D. Porter, 1866 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Letters received: S-T, 1866 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Letters received: W-Y, 1866 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Letters received: B-D, 1867 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Letters received: E-G, 1867 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Letters received: H-R, 1867 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Letters received: S, 1867 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Letters received: T-W, 1867 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Letters received: A-D, 1868 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Letters received: E-L, 1868 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Letters received: M-Z, 1868 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Letters received: A-L, 1869 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Letters received: M-P, 1869 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Letters received: R, 1869 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Letters received: W-Y, 1869 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Letters received, 1870 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Letters received, 1871 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Letters received, 1872 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Letters received: St. John's Portsmouth - credence table donation, 1872 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Letters received, 1873 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Letters received, 1874 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Letters received, 1875 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Letters received, 1876 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Letters received, 1877 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Letters received, 1878 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Letters received, 1879 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Letters received, 1880 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Letters received, 1881 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Letters received, 1882 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Letters received, 1883 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Letters received, Undated (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Architectural plans for Montgomery Meigs residence, Washington DC, 1869 (Box OS 2, Folder 6)
- Series II. Personal papers and documents (1838-1878)
  The series includes Fox's diaries, naval and civilian commissions, naval record of service, record of the sale of property, and other personal papers. His naval commissions are signed by Presidents Martin Van Buren (1838), John Tyler (1844), and Millard Fillmore (1851).
  - Diaries, 1866-1872 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Diaries, 1873-1876 June 15 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Diaries, 1876 June 16 - 1883 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Naval commissions, 1838, 1844, 1851 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Sale of property, Lawrence, Massachusetts, to Washington Mills Co., 1854-1864 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Mt. Auburn Cemetery plot: Purchase, correspondence, 1855, 1871 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Record of service in U.S. Navy, 1866, 1888, undated (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - U.S. tax return: draft version, 1869 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Certificates of membership: New England Historical Society, Massachusetts Historical Society, 1875, 1876 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Commission: Justice of the Peace, Suffolk County, Massachusetts, 1878 (Box OS 1, Folder 7)
- Series III. Speeches and writings (1861-1883)
  The materials up to 1862 document Fox's interests and activities including his plans for the reinforcement of Fort Sumter, and the value of steam battleships culminating in his support of Ericsson's design and construction of Monitor, as well as its battle with Virginia (originally Merrimack) at Hampton Roads in 1862. These papers appear to have been collected after the fact and include correspondence from John Ericsson and the draft of an unnamed publication on the subject. They are annotated by Virginia Woodbury Fox and document requests she received for information on the subject.
  Papers dating after the Civil War document Fox's 1866 mission to the court of Tsar Alexander II, his attempt to purchase the Southwest Pacific Railroad, his 1883 publication "The first landfall of Columbus: Is there extant evidence enough to prove the first landing place of Columbus in the new world?", and his interest in the history and topology of New Hampshire. The draft of his Columbus article is in a secretary's hand and edited in pencil, probably by Fox, and also shows Virginia Woodbury Fox's annotations. Some of the notes are numbered in pencil in order from 1 to 204, with no explanation provided for these notations.
  - Plans for reinforcing Fort Sumter, 1861 March (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Notes from British newspapers; writings on steamer specifications for U.S. Navy, 1862-1863 (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Monitor: Drafts, correspondence, 1862-1875 (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Monitor: Specifications, accounts of Hampton roads battle, Virginia Woodbury Fox notes, 1862-1895 (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - Mission to Russia: letters and writings, 1866 (Box 14, Folder 14)
  - Mission to Russia: Banquet menu, 1866 August (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Mission to Russia: Speech at presentation of Congressional resolution to Tsar Alexander II, 1866 Aug 8 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Mission to Russia: official dispatches, 1866-1867 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Mission to Russia: Letters and writings, 1866-1867 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Southwest Pacific Railroad: Correspondence, 1867 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Southwest Pacific Railroad: Correspondence with Charles L. Woodbury, 1867-1870 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Claims against Southwest Pacific Railroad, 1867-1873 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Claims against Southwest Pacific Railroad, 1867-1873 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Southwest Pacific Railroad: Correspondence, 1868-1869 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Southwest Pacific Railroad: Correspondence, 1870, 1873, 1876 (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Southwest Pacific Railroad: Letters and writings, Undated (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Atlantic and Pacific Railroad: Correspondence, statement, 1867, 1873 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Notes on New Hampshire history, topography, place names, [1877] (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - "Facts about Carroll Kearsage Mountain, of New Hampshire. Read before the Appalachian Mountain Club, by G.V. Fox", [1877] (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Speech at Philips Andover Academy centenary, 1878 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Landing of Columbus: Notes and correspondence, 1880-1881 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Landing of Columbus: Notes 1-107, 1881, undated (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Landing of Columbus: Notes 108-294, 1881, undated (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Landing of Columbus: Draft manuscripts, [1881] (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Landing of Columbus: Acknowledgments from libraries and individuals, 1882-1883 (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Writings and notes, undated (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Writings and notes, undated (Box 17, Folder 2)
- Series IV. Financial records (1869-1893)
  The series includes receipted bills, accounts, cancelled checks, and a check register. They document the Foxes' household and personal expenses in Washington, Boston (where they lived at the Parker House), and Lowell, Massachusetts, as well as his 1866-1868 travels to Russia through many European cities. The 1874 receipts include expenses for settlement of the estate of his mother, Mrs. Olivia Fox.
  - Cancelled checks, 1869 November - 1872 November (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Cancelled checks, 1872 November 4 - 1874 February 4 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Cancelled checks, 1874 July - 1878 March (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Check register, 1869 November 2 - 1872 November 4 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Receipts, 1866-1868 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Receipts: Boston and Lowell, 1874 (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Receipts: Boston, 1875 (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Receipts, 1876 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Receipts: Boston, 1877 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Receipts, 1878-1880 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Receipts, 1881-1882 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Receipts, 1883 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Accounts with E.R. Mudge & Co., 1874-1877 (Box 18, Folder 6)
- Series V. Memorabilia, souvenirs, and visual materials (1823-1890)
  The series includes an autograph collection, souvenirs of social and cultural events, calling cards received at home while the Foxes lived in Washington, drawings, photographs, and the illustrated manuscript of a satirical account of life aboard a steam battleship. The autographed letters include some addressed to President Andrew Jackson and then referred to the Secretary of the Navy, and show signatures of author Washington Irving, President Martin Van Buren, and politicians Robert Livingston and Thurlow Weed. The invitations include those to Lincoln's second inauguration in March, 1865; dinners with visiting Russian officers; and a ceremony marking the raising of the American flag over Fort Sumter after its recapture in 1865. Among the undated cards announcing an "at home" is one for the White House from President and Mrs. Lincoln.
  The drawings include some by Admiral David Porter, who is probably the author and illustrator of the satirical volume. The photographs include one of a woman, perhaps Virginia Woodbury Fox, alone, and with members of her family; as well as an unidentified older African-American woman.
  - Letters to and from distinguished men, 1823-1841, undated (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Invitations, passes, cards, 1861-1878 (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Invitations, passes, cards, [1860s] (Box 18, Folder 9)